<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ForDevelopers | The Recruiter Project]]></title>
  <link href="http://recruiterproject.org/blog/categories/fordevelopers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://recruiterproject.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-04T14:35:21-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://recruiterproject.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[The Recruiter Project]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Recruiters Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://recruiterproject.org/blog/2014/02/24/what-recruiters-do/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T11:47:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://recruiterproject.org/blog/2014/02/24/what-recruiters-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>What does a recruiter do, anyway?</h1>

<p>Recruiters just call you about &lsquo;great opportunities&rsquo; that are actually terrible, right? That may be all you are exposed to, so here is a bit about what recruiters actually do. Not all recruiters are great at what they do, just like not all developers are great at what they do, so this won&rsquo;t all apply to everyone that contacts you.</p>

<p>Wikipedia actually has a pretty thorough page: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recruiter">Recruiter</a>. Aside from that, the first couple of pages of search results that try to answer this question are covered in ads and seem a bit too spammy for my tastes. From Wikipedia, the breakdown is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Job analysis &ndash; figuring out actual job requirements</li>
<li>Sourcing &ndash; identifying candidates to fill job vacancies</li>
<li>Screening and Selection &ndash; filtering through potential people to find the best fit</li>
<li>Lateral hiring &ndash; &ldquo;sniping&rdquo; people based on their current jobs</li>
</ul>


<p>True North (a recruiting agency) <a href="http://www.truenorth-us.com/blog-and-news/news/162-five-things-a-recruiter-does-everyday">sums this up as</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Recruiters must be organized, possess strong people and sales skills, and maintain a strong work ethic to be successful. Here are five tasks that a recruiter juggles daily:</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Sourcing &ndash; identifying candidates to fill job vacancies</li>
<li>Host Interviews &ndash; interviewing potential people to find the best fit</li>
<li>Prepare Applicants for Client Interviews</li>
<li>Scan Resumes &ndash; in-between the rest of things, continually filter resumes for possible matches for all open jobs</li>
<li>Maintain Relationships With Placed Candidates &ndash; Making sure people stay at a job long enough for the recruiter to get paid, and the person may need a recruiters help in the future.</li>
</ul>


<h2>What you see</h2>

<p>Sourcing is the part that most people get to see, and it is the hardest and least-favorite part of most recruiters job&rsquo;s. Similarly to any kind of sales position, successful response rates to &lsquo;cold calls&rsquo; are very low and these are generally not well-received.</p>

<p>Recruiters know that more &lsquo;organic&rsquo; means of finding people is better, so they sponsor events like meet-ups and user groups, and they try to make things a fair trade.  As you grumble about how the recruiter spends 5 minutes talking about the jobs they are trying to fill, enjoy the pizza they bought for you and listen. Maybe they do have a job for you!</p>

<p>There are going to be some rough edges to all this, so enjoy the pizza and know that if you give a recruiter constructive feedback, they will be happy to hear it and are constantly trying to improve.</p>

<h2>What you don&rsquo;t see</h2>

<p>Recruiters much prefer matching up the right person with the right job, and giving you a call with a job offer. Jess Kimmet wrote a good post on this that answers more of &ldquo;What does a Recruiter like doing?&rdquo;:  <a href="http://www.volt.com/Blog/What_Does_a_Recruiter_Do_Anyway.aspx">What Does a Recruiter Do, Anyway?</a></p>

<blockquote><p>I work hard every day to leave a positive impression with everyone I work with. I may not be able to find a position for everyone, but I want them to know that I&rsquo;m on their side – and I&rsquo;d like nothing more than being able to call and say, &ldquo;Congratulations! You got the job.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Recruiters at recruiting agencies work with multiple companies and are almost always looking to fill multiple positions, so once they know about you and know your qualifications and what you&rsquo;re looking for, they will contact you when something pops up that you&rsquo;ll be a good fit for. The more great people a recruiter has &lsquo;on file&rsquo;, the better of a job they can do and the more the get paid. You being &lsquo;on file&rsquo; with more recruiters improves your chances of one of them getting it right.</p>

<h2>Working at an Agency</h2>

<p>Recruiters working at an Agency are typically working to fill jobs for multiple companies, and are paid based on how well they fill these jobs.  Here&rsquo;s a <a href="http://www.prestigestaffing.com/work-at-prestige/">job posting for Prestige Staffing</a>:</p>

<p>A Recruiter’s job duties include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Successfully recruiting and personally interviewing qualified job candidates</li>
<li>Working closely with account managers to plan and prioritize recruiting needs</li>
<li>Successfully matching candidates with clients’ employee requirements</li>
<li>Confidently and successfully negotiating terms of employment</li>
<li>Building and nurturing long-term relationships with candidates and clients</li>
<li>Capably multi-tasking in a fast-paced, demanding professional environment</li>
</ul>


<p>Job Qualifications:</p>

<ul>
<li>Bachelor’s Degree</li>
<li>Excellent oral communication skills</li>
<li>Positive attitude and strong work ethic</li>
<li>Coachable and enthusiastic about being part of a team</li>
<li>The intellect to “think on your feet,” solve problems, and make wise decisions</li>
<li>A strong desire to pursue a career in sales and management</li>
</ul>


<h2>Working as an &ldquo;in-house&rdquo; Recruiter</h2>

<p>Working in-house, recruiters are filling multiple jobs at one company. They are paid a salary and typically aren&rsquo;t paid based on exact numbers of jobs or hiring salaries.</p>

<p>Google is currently hiring a (probably a lot more than one) Recruiter: <a href="https://www.google.com/about/jobs/search/#!t=jo&amp;jid=3781001&amp;">Apply Here</a>. Here is what they are looking for:</p>

<p>Responsibilities</p>

<ul>
<li>Develop strong relationships with candidates, understanding their needs and helping them find a fit at Google.</li>
<li>Keep candidates continually informed with quality communications throughout the hiring process.</li>
<li>Solve problems and produce solutions by collecting and analyzing data, identifying alternatives when circumstances change and seeking out additional responsibilities.</li>
<li>Keep partners apprised of and involved in work by communicating information and status to project leads and team members, coordinating work cross-functionally and influencing peers, project leaders and/or managers.</li>
</ul>


<p>Qualifications</p>

<ul>
<li>BA/BS degree or equivalent practical experience.</li>
<li>2 years work experience in recruiting, sales or client service role.</li>
<li>Track record of solving complex problems and delivering significant impact.</li>
<li>Experience closing candidates and negotiating complex compensation packages.</li>
<li>Proven organizational skills with attention to detail and the ability to prioritize and succeed in an environment with competing demands.</li>
<li>Excellent verbal and written communication skills with an emphasis on tact and diplomacy.</li>
<li>Proven ability to take initiative, use consultative skills and build strong, productive relationships.</li>
<li>Exposure to HR processes, such as interviewing and candidate evaluation.</li>
<li>A track record of demonstrating a strong work ethic, integrity and personal accountability.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recruiters At Big Companies]]></title>
    <link href="http://recruiterproject.org/blog/2014/02/13/recruiters-in-big-companies/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-13T19:44:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://recruiterproject.org/blog/2014/02/13/recruiters-in-big-companies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been in California this week for <a href="http://strataconf.com/strata2014">Strata</a>, and I’ve gotten a chance to talk to a handful of recruiters about things from their perspective. This post is about recruiters that work full-time for big companies, I&rsquo;ll get to those that work for Agencies and small companies in future posts. First up are a few examples of what I think are great &ldquo;<a href="http://recruiterproject.org/blog/2014/02/10/making-first-contact/">First Contact</a>&rdquo; e-mails.</p>

<p>Before Strata, I got a LinkedIn message from a recruiter at Amazon that I&rsquo;d give a 9/10 to.  Nothing particularly targeted to me other than the fact that I&rsquo;m going to a conference, but that counts!</p>

<blockquote><p>Happy New Year from Amazon! I’m writing to let you know that if you’re planning on attending the Strata Conference in Santa Clara, Amazon will be speaking at the event. We’ll also be setting up informational interviews to discuss our exciting career opportunities and it would be great to connect with you at the conference. I’ve included a link to some of our job descriptions to give you an idea of what we’re working on and we’d love to see you there!</p>

<p>If you’re interested in learning more, please contact me and we can arrange a time to chat one-on-one. Be sure to stop by and say hello at booth 729!</p></blockquote>

<p>The link she included was to a &ldquo;Job Posting&rdquo; entitled: &ldquo;Come Visit Amazon at the Strata Conference&rdquo; which I&rsquo;ll paste here in case they &ldquo;fill&rdquo; that position:</p>

<blockquote><p>Job Description: Our mission is to be Earth’s most customer-centric company and we’re looking for Earth’s most talented Data Scientists, Software Developers, and Technical Program Managers to relentlessly pursue this mission with us.</p>

<p>Basic Qualifications:</p>

<ul>
<li>Work with massive data sets</li>
<li>Guide the optimization and efficiency of a market-leading program</li>
<li>Directly influence Amazon’s core business strategies</li>
<li>Solve complex technology problems</li>
<li>Work with world-class marketing and technology teams on creative analytical solutions</li>
<li>Significantly impact Amazon systems, businesses, and most importantly, our customers</li>
<li>Stretch your business and technical skills working with developers, data scientists, and business teams to design and implement game-changing features</li>
</ul>


<p>Preferred Qualifications</p>

<p>At Amazon, understanding extremely large sets of customer data is paramount to our success in providing a seamless customer experience across all platforms. Make an impact working with world-class marketing and technology teams on creative analytical solutions, guiding the optimization and efficiency of market-leading programs, and directly influence Amazon’s core business strategies.</p></blockquote>

<p>Fun, to the point, and not trying to get me to commit to anything.  I&rsquo;ve gotten similar well-played communications from other big companies like Google:</p>

<blockquote><p>I hope this message finds you well and I hope you&rsquo;re having a good day!</p>

<p>I wanted to reach out to you as I came across your information while researching candidates for a variety of engineering opportunities here at Google. Your experience could be interesting for a number of teams I work with.</p>

<p>Though I realize you might not be actively searching, I thought it would be beneficial for us to connect and possibly discuss Google in more detail.</p>

<p>Can we schedule a quick informal conversation in the next couple of weeks?</p></blockquote>

<p>How can these recruiters be so friendly when most of the e-mails you get are terrible and for jobs that are obviously not a match for you? It&rsquo;s because the incentives for these recruiters work differently, which causes their jobs to work differently.</p>

<p>The recruiting terminology for sending out these &lsquo;cold calls&rsquo; is &lsquo;Sourcing&rsquo; and from the people I&rsquo;ve talked to, its their least favorite thing about their jobs, but a necessary part of recruiting. Recruiters at agencies typically have quotas to meet, and almost universally their pay is dictated by how many people they hire. If you take a job through an agency, your new employer pays that agency some percentage (typically 10-20%) of your annual salary if you stick with the job for a few (typically 3-12) months.  This doesn&rsquo;t come out of your salary or make your salary any lower, it&rsquo;s simply a cost your employer pays to get new talent.</p>

<p>As for recruiters that don&rsquo;t work at agencies (like the ones I talked to this week), their salary isn&rsquo;t directly tied to head counts and hire salaries. Most of them don&rsquo;t even get bonuses for hiring tons of people and/or expensive/cheap people. They do have goals for positions they are trying to fill or number of hires in general, but they aren&rsquo;t incentivized to place you somewhere where you would be a poor fit.</p>

<p>These recruiters love their jobs and love making the perfect connection between a &lsquo;candidate&rsquo; (thats you!) and the right &lsquo;opportunity&rsquo; (your sweet new gig). Some of them got their start with Liberal Arts degrees, while some did something technical.  Some have technical work backgrounds too, while others have experience like coordinating volunteer efforts at non-profits.  All of them love working with people, traveling, managing events, and connecting people to great jobs.</p>

<p>Companies like Google and Amazon have very high standards for hiring (and even have specific processes in place to continue to raise the bar for who they hire), and these standards apply to the recruiters they hire too. They can quickly understand who you are, what you do, and what might be a good job for you at their companies, and direct you directly to the people you&rsquo;d need to talk with to find out for sure: specific managers, directors, VPs, engineers, etc.</p>

<p>A recruiter from a big company should be able to pull off a good &ldquo;First Contact&rdquo; e-mail, and is someone you should consider talking to, even if you aren&rsquo;t looking for a new job.  I&rsquo;ve gotten to speak with people that I wouldn&rsquo;t have met any other way about company culture, how hiring works, how career development works, and plenty of other things, all of which will be useful to me in the future. Knowing what is going on at other companies, especially ones that have a lot of smart people putting a lot of thought into it, will help you at your current job or help you figure out what you want to do next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
